لِمَنِ الْمُلْكُ الْيَوْمَ ۖ لِلَّهِ الْوَاحِدِ الْقَهَّارِ ﴿16﴾
To whom belongs [all] sovereignty this Day? To Allah, the One, the Prevailing.
الْيَوْمَ تُجْزَىٰ كُلُّ نَفْسٍ بِمَا كَسَبَتْ ۚ لَا ظُلْمَ الْيَوْمَ ۚ
This Day every soul will be recompensed for what it earned. No injustice today!
إِنَّ اللَّهَ سَرِيعُ الْحِسَابِ ﴿17﴾
Indeed, Allah is swift in account.
وَأَنْذِرْهُمْ يَوْمَ الْآزِفَةِ إِذِ الْقُلُوبُ لَدَى الْحَنَاجِرِ كَاظِمِينَ ۚ
And warn them, [O Muhammad], of the Approaching Day, when hearts are at the throats, filled [with distress].
إِذِ الْقُلُوبُ لَدَى الْحَنَاجِرِ كَاظِمِينَ ۚ مَا لِلظَّالِمِينَ مِنْ حَمِيمٍ
when hearts are at the throats, filled [with distress]. For the wrongdoers there will be no devoted friend
مَا لِلظَّالِمِينَ مِنْ حَمِيمٍ وَلَا شَفِيعٍ يُطَاعُ ﴿18﴾
For the wrongdoers there will be no devoted friend and no intercessor [who is] obeyed.
حم ﴿1﴾ تَنْزِيلُ الْكِتَابِ مِنَ اللَّهِ الْعَزِيزِ الْعَلِيمِ ﴿2﴾
Ha, Meem. The revelation of the Book is from Allah, the Exalted in Might, the Knowing.
غَافِرِ الذَّنْبِ وَقَابِلِ التَّوْبِ شَدِيدِ الْعِقَابِ ذِي الطَّوْلِ ۖ لَا إِلَٰهَ إِلَّا هُوَ ۖ إِلَيْهِ الْمَصِيرُ ﴿3﴾
The forgiver of sin, acceptor of repentance, severe in punishment, owner of abundance. There is no deity except Him; to Him is the destination.
مَا يُجَادِلُ فِي آيَاتِ اللَّهِ إِلَّا الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا فَلَا يَغْرُرْكَ تَقَلُّبُهُمْ فِي الْبِلَادِ ﴿4﴾
No one disputes concerning the signs of Allah except those who disbelieve, so be not deceived by their movement throughout the land.
كَذَّبَتْ قَبْلَهُمْ قَوْمُ نُوحٍ وَالْأَحْزَابُ مِنْ بَعْدِهِمْ ۖ
The people of Noah denied before them and the [disbelieving] factions after them,
وَهَمَّتْ كُلُّ أُمَّةٍ بِرَسُولِهِمْ لِيَأْخُذُوهُ ۖ وَجَادَلُوا بِالْبَاطِلِ
and every nation intended [a plot] for their messenger to seize him, and they disputed by [using] falsehood
وَجَادَلُوا بِالْبَاطِلِ لِيُدْحِضُوا بِهِ الْحَقَّ فَأَخَذْتُهُمْ ۖ فَكَيْفَ كَانَ عِقَابِ ﴿5﴾
and they disputed by [using] falsehood to [attempt to] invalidate thereby the truth. So I seized them, and how [terrible] was My penalty.
وَكَذَٰلِكَ حَقَّتْ كَلِمَتُ رَبِّكَ عَلَى الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا أَنَّهُمْ أَصْحَابُ النَّارِ ﴿6﴾
And thus has the word of your Lord come into effect upon those who disbelieved that they are companions of the Fire.
الَّذِينَ يَحْمِلُونَ الْعَرْشَ وَمَنْ حَوْلَهُ يُسَبِّحُونَ بِحَمْدِ رَبِّهِمْ وَيُؤْمِنُونَ بِهِ
Those [angels] who carry the Throne and those around it exalt [Allah] with praise of their Lord and believe in Him
يُسَبِّحُونَ بِحَمْدِ رَبِّهِمْ وَيُؤْمِنُونَ بِهِ وَيَسْتَغْفِرُونَ لِلَّذِينَ آمَنُوا
exalt [ Allah ] with praise of their Lord and believe in Him and ask forgiveness for those who have believed,
رَبَّنَا وَسِعْتَ كُلَّ شَيْءٍ رَحْمَةً وَعِلْمًا فَاغْفِرْ لِلَّذِينَ تَابُوا
[saying], "Our Lord, You have encompassed all things in mercy and knowledge, so forgive those who have repented
فَاغْفِرْ لِلَّذِينَ تَابُوا وَاتَّبَعُوا سَبِيلَكَ وَقِهِمْ عَذَابَ الْجَحِيمِ ﴿7﴾
so forgive those who have repented and followed Your way and protect them from the punishment of Hellfire.
رَبَّنَا وَأَدْخِلْهُمْ جَنَّاتِ عَدْنٍ الَّتِي وَعَدْتَهُمْ وَمَنْ صَلَحَ مِنْ آبَائِهِمْ
Our Lord, and admit them to gardens of perpetual residence which You have promised them and whoever was righteous among their fathers,
وَمَنْ صَلَحَ مِنْ آبَائِهِمْ وَأَزْوَاجِهِمْ وَذُرِّيَّاتِهِمْ
and whoever was righteous among their fathers, their spouses and their offspring.
إِنَّكَ أَنْتَ الْعَزِيزُ الْحَكِيمُ ﴿8﴾
Indeed, it is You who is the Exalted in Might, the Wise.
وَقِهِمُ السَّيِّئَاتِ ۚ وَمَنْ تَقِ السَّيِّئَاتِ يَوْمَئِذٍ فَقَدْ رَحِمْتَهُ ۚ
And protect them from the evil consequences. And he whom You protect from evil consequences that Day - You will have given him mercy.
وَذَٰلِكَ هُوَ الْفَوْزُ الْعَظِيمُ ﴿9﴾
And that is the great attainment."
إِنَّ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا يُنَادَوْنَ لَمَقْتُ اللَّهِ أَكْبَرُ مِنْ مَقْتِكُمْ أَنْفُسَكُمْ
Indeed, those who disbelieve will be addressed, "The hatred of Allah for you was [even] greater than your hatred of yourselves
لَمَقْتُ اللَّهِ أَكْبَرُ مِنْ مَقْتِكُمْ أَنْفُسَكُمْ إِذْ تُدْعَوْنَ إِلَى الْإِيمَانِ فَتَكْفُرُونَ ﴿10﴾
"The hatred of Allah for you was [even] greater than your hatred of yourselves [this Day in Hell] when you were invited to faith, but you refused."
قَالُوا رَبَّنَا أَمَتَّنَا اثْنَتَيْنِ وَأَحْيَيْتَنَا اثْنَتَيْنِ فَاعْتَرَفْنَا بِذُنُوبِنَا
They will say, "Our Lord, You made us lifeless twice and gave us life twice, and we have confessed our sins.
فَاعْتَرَفْنَا بِذُنُوبِنَا فَهَلْ إِلَىٰ خُرُوجٍ مِنْ سَبِيلٍ ﴿11﴾
and we have confessed our sins. So is there to an exit any way?"
ذَٰلِكُمْ بِأَنَّهُ إِذَا دُعِيَ اللَّهُ وَحْدَهُ كَفَرْتُمْ ۖ وَإِنْ يُشْرَكْ بِهِ تُؤْمِنُوا ۚ
[They will be told], "That is because, when Allah was called upon alone, you disbelieved; but if others were associated with Him, you believed.
فَالْحُكْمُ لِلَّهِ الْعَلِيِّ الْكَبِيرِ ﴿12﴾
So the judgement is with Allah, the Most High, the Grand."
هُوَ الَّذِي يُرِيكُمْ آيَاتِهِ وَيُنَزِّلُ لَكُمْ مِنَ السَّمَاءِ رِزْقًا ۚ
It is He who shows you His signs and sends down to you from the sky, provision.
وَمَا يَتَذَكَّرُ إِلَّا مَنْ يُنِيبُ ﴿13﴾
But none will remember except he who turns back [in repentance].
فَادْعُوا اللَّهَ مُخْلِصِينَ لَهُ الدِّينَ وَلَوْ كَرِهَ الْكَافِرُونَ ﴿14﴾
So invoke Allah, [being] sincere to Him in religion, although the disbelievers dislike it.
رَفِيعُ الدَّرَجَاتِ ذُو الْعَرْشِ يُلْقِي الرُّوحَ مِنْ أَمْرِهِ عَلَىٰ مَنْ يَشَاءُ مِنْ عِبَادِهِ
[He is] the Exalted above [all] degrees, Owner of the Throne; He places the inspiration of His command upon whom He wills of His servants
يُلْقِي الرُّوحَ مِنْ أَمْرِهِ عَلَىٰ مَنْ يَشَاءُ مِنْ عِبَادِهِ لِيُنْذِرَ يَوْمَ التَّلَاقِ ﴿15﴾
He places the inspiration of His command upon whom He wills of His servants to warn of the Day of Meeting.
لِيُنْذِرَ يَوْمَ التَّلَاقِ ﴿15﴾ يَوْمَ هُمْ بَارِزُونَ ۖ
to warn of the Day of Meeting. The Day they come forth
لَا يَخْفَىٰ عَلَى اللَّهِ مِنْهُمْ شَيْءٌ ۚ
nothing concerning them will be concealed from Allah
لِمَنِ الْمُلْكُ الْيَوْمَ ۖ لِلَّهِ الْوَاحِدِ الْقَهَّارِ ﴿16﴾
To whom belongs [all] sovereignty this Day? To Allah, the One, the Prevailing.
الْيَوْمَ تُجْزَىٰ كُلُّ نَفْسٍ بِمَا كَسَبَتْ ۚ لَا ظُلْمَ الْيَوْمَ ۚ
This Day every soul will be recompensed for what it earned. No injustice today!
إِنَّ اللَّهَ سَرِيعُ الْحِسَابِ ﴿17﴾
Indeed, Allah is swift in account.
وَأَنْذِرْهُمْ يَوْمَ الْآزِفَةِ إِذِ الْقُلُوبُ لَدَى الْحَنَاجِرِ كَاظِمِينَ ۚ
And warn them, [O Muhammad], of the Approaching Day, when hearts are at the throats, filled [with distress].
إِذِ الْقُلُوبُ لَدَى الْحَنَاجِرِ كَاظِمِينَ ۚ مَا لِلظَّالِمِينَ مِنْ حَمِيمٍ
when hearts are at the throats, filled [with distress]. For the wrongdoers there will be no devoted friend
مَا لِلظَّالِمِينَ مِنْ حَمِيمٍ وَلَا شَفِيعٍ يُطَاعُ ﴿18﴾
For the wrongdoers there will be no devoted friend and no intercessor [who is] obeyed.
يَعْلَمُ خَائِنَةَ الْأَعْيُنِ وَمَا تُخْفِي الصُّدُورُ ﴿19﴾
He knows that which deceives the eyes and what the breasts conceal.
وَاللَّهُ يَقْضِي بِالْحَقِّ ۖ وَالَّذِينَ يَدْعُونَ مِنْ دُونِهِ لَا يَقْضُونَ بِشَيْءٍ ۗ إِنَّ اللَّهَ هُوَ السَّمِيعُ الْبَصِيرُ ﴿20﴾
And Allah judges with truth, while those they invoke besides Him judge not with anything. Indeed, Allah - He is the Hearing, the Seeing.
لِمَنِ الْمُلْكُ الْيَوْمَ ۖ لِلَّهِ الْوَاحِدِ الْقَهَّارِ ﴿16﴾
To whom belongs [all] sovereignty this Day? To Allah, the One, the Prevailing.